大地惊雷
小法兰
Little Frank.
- 你要照顾妈妈 - 我会的
- You take care of your ma. - I will.
- 汤姆 没太多行李吧 - 带齐了
- You're not travelling heavy, Tom. - I got all I need.
你该坐火车 史密斯堡很远的
You should be taking the train, Frank. Fort Smith is too long a ride.
骑茱迪走七十里路会很轻松
On Judy, 70 miles will be just a pleasant outing.
逸尼 你替我打点这里吧
Yarnell, you'll take care of the place for me.
你和美蒂...美蒂在哪里?
You and my Mattie. Where's Mattie?
爸 我在这里
I'm here, Papa!
小掌柜 现金准备好了吗?
Well, Little Bookkeeper, got my wherewithal ready?
- 好了 - 你准我用多少钱?
- Of course. - How much are you allowing me?
大约有...
There's... right around...
现金一百五十元
...$150 cash money there.
把幸运金币也给我吧
Better hand me my good luck gold pieces, too.
买德州小野马需要很多运气
Buying Texas mustang ponies, you'll need plenty of luck!
你会赞成大量买入马匹的计划
You'll come around to my plan. I intend to buy as many as I can swing.
- 繁殖用来猎鹿 - 它们既小又笨
- We'll breed them for deer- hunting. - They're small and chicken- brained!
是既小又勇 与猎犬最配合
I'd say small and tough, right for keeping up with dogs.
- 爸 想听我意见吗 - 经常都听
- You want my advice, Papa? - I always do.
- 以平价买那小马 - 我也这么想
- Buy the ponies cheap. - I expect to.
史东晓上校要在冬季前卖掉它们
This Colonel Stonehill has got to get rid of them before winter.
枪很旧了 在史密斯堡买新的吧
Papa, that gun's old- fashioned. Buy a new one at Fort Smith.
它在切马加立下大功 它仍有用
It served me well at Chickamauga, and it's got a long way to go yet.
爸 再见
Goodbye, Papa!
程汤姆...那个人是混蛋
Tom Chaney... Now there's trash for you.
看管这里是他的职责
It's his job to look after the place.
他挨饿时爸收留他和给他一间屋
Papa took him in when he was starving and gave him a house.
那只是间很旧的工具室
Come, Mattie, it's only an old tool- shed.
南面的墙烂得可以扔猫进去
You can still throw a cat through the south wall!
屋顶完好无缺
It's got a good roof.
- 这是骗局 - 什么?
- This game's crooked! - What?
你们作弊
You've been dealing me seconds!
骗子 你迭牌的
Goddamn crooks! You're stackin' the decks!
走吧 汤姆 我们想早点回家
Come on, Tom. We want to make an early start for home.
我要去拿回我的钱
I'm going back in there. I want to get my money back!
你喝醉酒和拿着枪就不能去
Not full of whisky and with a gun. That's no way.
- 有枪好办事 - 你不许去惹麻烦
- A gun'll say a whole lot quick. - I won't allow you to get into trouble.
- 把枪给我 - 给你个屁
- Gimme your gun. - I'll give you one end of it!
把枪给我
Gimme the gun! Gimme your gun!
(史密斯堡)
上车
All aboard!
殡仪馆在哪里?
Where's the undertaker?
在法院转角处
Round the corner from the courthouse, ma'am.
谢谢你
Thank you.
我不明白为何这里有这么多人
I can't understand all these people being here.
所有人从四面八方走来
Everybody comes in from every place.
- 我想知道原因 - 他们今天行刑
- I'd like to know why. - They're hanging three men today.
我们还是去看爸爸吧
We'd better go and see about Papa.
(暂停营业 去了刑场)
看来他去了找生意
Looks like he's out rustling up business for himself.
我们有时间打发了
Seems like we have some time to waste before we see anybody.
我看得出你想去看问吊
I can tell you want to go to the hanging.
不可以 你妈吩咐我照顾你
Afraid I can't. Your mama said keep an eye on you.
我也会去看
Well, I'll go along.
放心 我不会告诉妈的
Don't worry, I won't tell Mama.
我曾经迷途
I was once lost
但现在已被寻获
But now am found
我曾经失明 但现在能看见
Was blind but now I see
是主的大恩教晦...
'Twas grace that taught
我的心畏惧
My heart to fear
主恩解除我的惊恐
And grace my fears relieved
那声音多么甜美...
How sweet the sound...
在露台上的那个人
That man up there on the porch...
是白加法官 他监督所有行刑
That's Judge Parker. He watches all the hangings.
- 他说是他的职责 - 谁知道他心里想什么?
- He says it's his sense of duty. - Who knows what's in a man's heart?
阿门
... Amen.
那个刽子手是北方佬
The hangman's a Yankee.
人们说他不会问吊穿蓝衣的人
They say he won't spring the trap on a boy that wore the blue.
不要 我来了就要全部看完
No, I'm here, I'll see it all.
我的天
My goodness!
不是个胆怯的法官
That's not a faint- hearted judge.
程汤姆要在这样的法官面前服法
Chaney'll get his due before such a judge.
(安息)
是他吗?
Is that the man?
这是我的父亲
That is my father.
若你想吻他 不要紧
If you would like to kiss him, it would be all right.
不了...
No...
盖棺吧
Put the lid on it.
我是耶路县特丹镇的罗美蒂
I'm Mattie Ross of Dardanelle in Yell County.
这是我的朋友兼家仆彭逸尼
And this is my friend, Yarnell Pointdexter, who works on our place.
小姐 有何事情
Yes, ma'am. State your business.
家父在史密斯堡被程汤姆所杀
My father was killed in Fort Smith by a coward named Tom Chaney.
你们怎样处理这宗谋杀案?
What are you doing about the murder?
我们知他姓钱 在印第安人领土
We do know this: His name's Chambers, he's in Indian territory.
他周二在蒲托河打劫了一辆邮车
We think he robbed a mail hack Tuesday down on the Poteau River.
中等身材 脸上有一块黑斑
He's medium height, with a black mark on his cheek.
那是程汤姆 不是姓钱的
That's Tom Chaney. There's no Chambers to it.
他脸上的黑斑是中枪的伤痕
He got that black mark when a man fired a pistol in his face.
- 何不去找他 - 我没权去红蕃区
- Why aren't you out looking for him? - I've no authority in the Indian Nation.
现在由美国执法官抓他
He's now the business of the US Marshal.
- 谁是最好执法官 - 韦比擅追踪
- Who's the best marshal they have? - Bill Waters is the best tracker.
郭洛达 心狠手辣、智勇双全
The meanest one is Rooster Cogburn, double- tough, knows no fear.
昆恩最严明 要生擒他们
L T Quinn is the straightest. He brings them in alive.
- 哪里找到郭 - 下午在联邦法庭
- Where would I find this Rooster? - At the Federal Court this afternoon.
他会押本区的犯人到来
He's bringing in prisoners from the territory.
- 有程吗 - 不知 这是联邦事务
- Is Chaney one of them? - I don't know. That's federal business.
你想把令尊的枪带回家吧
Your father's gun... you'll want to take it home, I expect.
他的马鞍在史东晓上校的牧畜棚
His saddle is at Colonel Stonehill's stock barn,
其他的遗物都在帝王旅馆
and the rest of his things are at the Monarch boarding house.
我要把程汤姆杀死才会罢休
I won't rest till Tom Chaney's barking in hell!
逸尼...
Yarnell...
你留下来陪爸爸
You stay with Papa.
回家后替他换有美臣围边的棺木
When you get home, put him in a better coffin with Mason's apron.
你妈要你回家
Your mama wants you home.
妈知我应付得到 叫她别签文件
Mama knows I can take care of myself. Tell her not to sign anything till I return.
人家会误会我丢下这件事给你办
People'll take it wrong that I leave this to you,
但我要处理爸的事情
but I got Papa's business to see to.
告诉妈我会住在帝王旅馆
Tell Mama I'm staying at the Monarch boarding house.
我会去查看程汤姆可有被押回来
I'm going to see if Tom Chaney's been brought in.
然后去见郭洛达
And then I'll see this Rooster Cogburn.
好了 让开 退后
All right, get outta the way! Back up!
站起来
Stand up!
出来
Come on out!
快点
Move along!
这些囚犯是否来自印第安人区?
Are the prisoners from the Indian Territory?
- 是的 - 当中有没有程汤姆?
- Yes, ma'am. - Is one of them Tom Chaney?
郭还没有交出他的名单
Cogburn ain't turned in his list yet.
- 谁是郭洛达? - 高大、独眼的
- Which marshal is Rooster Cogburn? - The big fella with the eye- patch.
走吧
Come on!
开走它
All right, take it away!
- 郭先生 - 等一等 回来
- Mr Cogburn! - Wait! Come back here!
郭先生
Mr Cogburn!
回来
Come back here!
上来吧
All right, come on up.
他以为关上门就难倒我 他错了
If he thinks I'm put off by a locked door, he doesn't know me!
- 我会等到开门 - 你会肚饿的
- I'll be here when it opens. - Then you'll be mighty hungry.
最好明天来找他
Best time to nail him is tomorrow.
他要在白加法官面前作证
He's testifying before Judge Parker.
谢谢 你真好人
Thank you very much. I appreciate your kindness.
还想吃汤团吗?
Have some more dumplings, dear?
一顿饭收两毛五仙 不妨吃吃
At 25 cents per meal, I might just as well.
我以为你喜欢吃
I was hoping you were enjoying them.
少许面粉和油可不值两毛五仙
They're all right. I can't see 25 cents in a little flour and grease.
- 赖宝先生 你迟到了 - 法文是赖博
- You're late, Mr La Boof. - The French is 'La Boeuf'.
我叫它做赖比
I call it 'La Beef'.
赖比先生今晚来了
Mr La Beef came in this evening.
请除下马刺
Your spurs, please.
我的椅已被刮得伤痕累累了
My poor chairs are scratched enough already.
先生 很夺目的装束呢
A right fancy rig, sir.
小心那些鸡肉和汤团
Watch out for the chicken and dumplings.
- 它们有损眼睛 - 为什么?
- They'll hurt your eyes. - How's that?
你想找鸡肉就很伤神
They'll hurt your eyes looking for the chicken!
你这个蠢混蛋
You squirrel- headed bastard!
你好 你叫什么名字?
Howdy. What's your name?
我去睡了 但我想看我爸的行李
I'd like to go to bed now. But first I'd like to see my father's traps.
我猜你的名字是罗美蒂
I'll take a guess and say your name is Mattie Ross.
- 赖比很英俊 - 他要洗澡剃须
- Mr La Beef is a handsome man. - He needs a bath and a shave.
- 他从德州来 - 他满意他的发型
- He hails from Texas. - Judge he's proud of his cowlick.
- 他怎知我名字 - 他擅长猜测吧
- How did he guess my name? - He's a good guesser, I guess!
因为举行问吊 房间短缺
We're short of rooms on account of the hanging.
你要跟邓娜婆婆同房
You'll sleep in here with Grandma Turner.
别担心 她习惯了跟人同房
Don't worry about Grandma Turner, she's used to doubling up.
那么我的租金会减半吧?
I take it my rent will be half, then?
你爸的行李 手表和刀都在里面
These are your father's traps. The watch and the knife are inside.
程偷了他的钱和马
Chaney stole his money and his horse.
你觉得郭洛达执法官为人怎样
What do you think of Marshal Rooster Cogburn?
郭洛达 我听过他一些可怕的事
Rooster Cogburn! I've heard some terrible things about him!
我知道他嗜好杯中物
He loves to pull a cork, I know that!
白加法官大人 全体起立
His Honour, Judge Parker! All rise!
我要吃颗薄荷糖纾缓胃部
I'll have a peppermint to settle my stomach.
是 大人
Yes, sir.
美国西部法庭...
The United States Court of the Western District,
拥有印弟安人领土司法权 开庭
having criminal jurisdiction in the Indian Territory, is now in session.
那就是行刑法官白加法官?
Is that Judge Parker, the hanging judge?
他很严的 除了总统 不得上诉
He's a tough customer. There's no appeal except to the President himself!
传召郭副执法官上庭
Call Deputy Marshal Cogburn.
郭洛达先生请上证人栏
Mr Reuben J Cogburn will take the stand.
你今早发过誓 仍然有效
You were sworn this morning, you're still sworn.
辩方作盘问
Defence will cross- examine.
郭先生 你今早曾代表控方作证
Mr Cogburn, you testified for the prosecution this morning.
容许我总结你的话 你声称...
Allow me to summarise what you said. According to your story...
韦顿攫取了枪把柏特执法官杀死
...C C Wharton grabbed a shotgun and killed Marshal Potter.
然后用枪指着你 你就把他射死
Then he turned the gun on you, and you shot him.
他的父亲挥动斧头 你也射死他
Then the father swung his axe, and you shot him, too.
你说被告逃跑 你也射他
The defendant tried to run, you say, and you also shot him.
只是击中他 否则他不会来服刑
Just winged him, or he wouldn't be here to pay up!
那老头和韦顿倒在地上死去
The old man and CC hit the ground dead.
郭先生 你当了执法官多久?
How long have you been a Deputy Marshal, Mr Cogburn?
今年三月就四年了
Four years, come March.
你开枪射过多少人?
How many men have you shot in that time?
- 控方反对 - 反对无效
- The prosecution objects! - Overruled!
你当上执法官后射过多少人?
How many men have you shot since becoming a marshal?
- 我不会滥杀无辜 - 答非所问 有多少人
- I never shot nobody I didn't have to! - That's not the question. How many?
开枪还是杀死的?
Shot or killed?
限指杀死吧 数目较易统计
Let's restrict it to killed, a more manageable figure!
12至15个 制止逃跑和自卫
Well, twelve to fifteen, stopping men in flight and defending myself.
12至15个? 多到你数不清
Twelve to fifteen? So many you can't keep a specific count.
我翻查过记录
I have examined the records.
一个更准确的数字 究竟多少?
A more accurate figure is available. Come now, how many?
把韦氏父子算在内 23个
Counting them two Whartons, twenty- three.
你下了一番工夫才有这个成绩吧
I felt you'd come to it with a little effort.
四年内杀23人 大约每年六个
Twenty- three dead men in four years. That makes about six men a year!
- 工作很危险 - 还拘捕了很多人
- It's a dangerous business. - How much more for those you arrest!
你是否拔出一支六发左轮手枪...
Is it not true that you sprang upon the Whartons
指向韦氏父子?
with a deadly six- shot revolver?
- 我经常戒备 - 手枪是否有子弹
- I always try to be ready. - Was this revolver loaded and cocked?
没上子弹的手枪毫无用处
A gun that's unloaded ain't good for nothing!
请你回答
Just answer, if you please.
- 这问题不合理 - 别跟律师斗嘴
- The question don't make sense! - Don't bandy words with counsel.
是 大人
Yes, sir.
你作证说你曾后退离开韦父
You testified you backed away from old man Wharton.
- 是的 - 哪个方向?
- Yes, sir. - Which direction?
后面 我后退时永远是去后面的
Backward! I always go backward when I'm backing away!
这句话很幽默
I appreciate the humour of that remark.
你抵达时韦亚伦正站在一个壶边
Aaron Wharton was standing by a pot when you arrived?
是蹲着 他在拨壶下面的火
More like squatting. He was stirring the fire under the pot.
- 你后退了多远? - 六至八步
- How far did you back away? - Six, eight steps.
即是说韦也行前了一样的距离?
Meaning Wharton advanced the same distance? Six or eight steps?
- 十六步? - 大概是的
- Sixteen feet? - Something like that.
为何尸体发现在水壶旁边...
Then explain why the body was found by the wash pot,
一手臂在火里 衣袖和手在闷烧
one arm in the flames, the sleeve and hand smouldering.
那些混蛋 他们移动了尸体
Them hogs! They may have moved the body.
混蛋 不错
Hogs, indeed!
葛迪先生 还有问题吗?
Mr Goudy, do you have any more questions?
完全没有直接答案 我问完了
None that I'll get a straight answer to. I'm finished with him.
郭先生 你可以离开了
You're dismissed, Mr Cogburn.
传召下一位证人
Call the next witness!
传霍西素上庭
Cecil Falling Leaf, take the stand!
请举起右手...
Raise your right hand...
- 郭洛达先生? - 什么事?
- Mr Rooster Cogburn? - What is it?
我想和你谈 他们说你很有胆识
I'd like to talk with you a minute. They say you're a man with true grit.
你想怎样? 快说
What do you want? Speak up!
你已经把烟纸弄皱了
You've already wrinkled the paper...
它很松散因为你的烟叶太干了
It's pretty loose because your makings are too dry.
我要找程汤姆
I'm looking for Tom Chaney.
他是谁?
Well, who's he?
他开枪杀死了我父亲罗法伦
He shot and killed my father, Frank Ross.
他在印第安人区 我要找人追他
He's in the Indian Territory. I need somebody to go after him.
- 你是谁? - 罗美蒂
- Who are you? - Mattie Ross.
我家在耶路县有480亩优质土地
My family has 480 acres of good bottomland in Yell County.
我妈在家中照顾我年幼的弟妹
Mother's home looking after my baby sister and brother.
你为何不回家? 别烦我了
Why don't you go home and leave me alone?
他们要人帮忙搅牛乳
They'll need help with the churning!
郭先生
Mr Cogburn!
你可抓到程汤姆和获得两元报酬
You can get a fugitive warrant for Chaney and $2 for bringing him in,
每里另得一角 我给你50元奖金
plus 10 cents a mile for each of you, and I'll give you $50 reward!
你对这件事了如指掌呢
You've looked into this right smart.
是的 我是认真的
Yes, I mean business.
他袋里有什么?
What have you got in your poke?
天 这是一支高尔特龙骑枪
By God, girl, that's a Colt's Dragoon!
你是个小孩 带着这支枪干嘛?
You're no bigger than a corn nubbin. What are you doing with this pistol?
我父亲在战时勇敢地戴着它
My father carried it bravely in the war.
若执法失败 我打算用它来杀程
I intend to kill Tom Chaney with it if the law fails.
可以 若你找到栏杆来承托它...
This'll sure get the job done, if you can find a fence post to rest it on
然后瞄准
while you take aim!
恐怕要我亲自下手才抓到程了
I'm afraid nothing'll be done about Chaney unless I do it myself.
- 你没有50元 - 马匹交易后就有
- I don't think you've got $50. - After my horse- trading, I'll have it.
你可认识枪匪[好运」白尼特?
Do you know the robber Lucky Ned Pepper?
我认识他
I know him... well!
去年八月在旋梯山射中他的嘴唇
I shot him in the lip last August over at Winding Stair Mountains.
当天他走运 我射不中他
He was lucky that day, my shooting was off!
我相信程是跟他一伙的
Well, I think Chaney's tied up with him.
- 是吗? - 是的
- Yeah? - Yeah!
- 白尼特? - 是
- Ned Pepper, huh? - Yeah...
小妹妹 你拿不到50元
Baby sister, I don't think you can get $50.
不过我会带你回家吃饭
But I'll take you home and give you supper.
我们再商量一下 怎么样?
We'll talk it over, make medicine. How does that suit you?
好提议
Right down to the ground.
我想认识你的家人
I'd like to meet your family.
这是家父陈利
This is my father, Chen Lee.
和我的侄儿[优秀将军」
And my nephew, General Sterling Price.
还要吗 小姐?
You want more, Missy?
我够了 像吃完盛宴一样饱
I've had enough, and enough is as good as a feast.
我从来没看过筷子
I've never seen chopsticks work before.
筷子可空出手指
Chopsticks save the fingers.
- 把你的杯给我 - 我不喝咖啡的
- Gimme your cup. - I don't drink coffee, thank you.
- 你喝什么? - 我爱喝脱脂冻奶
- Well, what do you drink? - I'm partial to cold buttermilk.
我们没有冻奶 也没有柠檬汁
Well, we ain't got none of that. We ain't got no lemonade either.
我们来玩扑克牌吧
Let's get to the game.
- 我发牌? - 是的
- My deal? - Yes, sir.
- 我的提议怎样? - 正在考虑
- What about my proposition? - Thinking on it.
听来很容易就赚到50元
Sounds like a mighty easy way to make $50 to me.
别逼我 我在考虑费用
Don't crowd me, I'm figuring expenses.
你怎能同时玩牌、喝酒和想捉贼
How you can play cards, drink whisky and think detective at the same time?
若我要对付白尼特就要花一百元
Well, if I have to go up against Ned Pepper, it'll cost $100, I figure.
还要预支50元
And 50 in advance.
- 你想利用我 - 是我的最低工资
- You're trying to take advantage of me. - They're my children's rates!
要对付尼特不简单
It isn't going to be easy smoking old Ned out.
他会匿藏在那个印第安人区
He'll be holed up down that Indian Nation.
我不会让你喝威士忌的
Well, I'm not going to keep you in whisky!
我不用买的 只需充公它
I don't buy that, I confiscate it!
喝一点可以驱除晚上的寒风
A touch of it wouldn't do you any harm against the night air!
它是最了不起 顶呱呱的好货
It's the real article, genuine double- rectified bust- head!
在肚里变醇
Aged in the keg.
我不会胡言乱语充昏我的头脑
I wouldn't put a thief in my mouth to steal my brains.
我的价钱是一百元 成交吗?
Well, sis, my price is $100. There it is. Want to make medicine?
我会考虑你的建议
I will think about your proposition.
你陪我去那间旅馆吧
You better walk me over to the boarding house.
你真是麻烦
You are a lot of trouble.
等我玩完这一手吧
Wait till I finish this hand.
你猜不透中国人 他就这样赢你
You can't tell what's in a Chinaman's mind. That's the way he bests you!
我去
I go.
走开
Scat!
老鼠先生...
Mr Rat...
我要你立刻停止吃陈利的麦片
My writ here says you must stop eating Chen Lee's cornmeal forthwith.
这是老鼠逮捕令 一样有法制的
It's a rat writ, writ for a rat, and this is lawful service of same.
它不理会我
See, he doesn't pay any attention to me.
要开枪就出外面
Outside is the place for shooting!
我在执行任务
I'm serving some papers.
那本来是你的职责
That was your job in the first place!
小妹妹不能发逮捕令捉鼠辈的
You can't serve papers on a rat, baby sister.
你要杀死他或者放过他
You've got to kill him or let him be.
你要把那个喝光?
Are you going to drink all of that?
白加法宫...投机的老头
Judge Parker... Old Carpetbagger!
他认识鼠辈 我们曾有个好法庭
But he knows his rats. We had a good court...
那些诡辩的律师到来就改变了
...until those pettifogging lawyers moved in.
捕鼠者对那些鼠辈太严苛了
The ratcatcher's too tough on the rats!
他们说： [给那些鼠辈公道」
"Give them rats a fair show," they say.
他们又给过柏特什么公道?
What fair show did they give old man Potter?
说吧 好人总是活不了的
Tell me that. Finer man never lived.
你这个样子是没用的
You're useless in this condition.
我自己去好了
I'll walk over there by myself.
- 你怕黑吗? - 不怕
- You scared of the dark? - Never!
我有那样的马枪也不会害怕鬼怪
If I had a big horse- pistol like that, I wouldn't be scared of the booger man.
我不害怕鬼怪
I'm not scared of no booger man.
- 要糖吗? - 不 谢谢
- Sugar? - No thanks.
- 牛奶 - 麻烦你
- Cream? - Please.
一点点好了
Just a dab.
罗小姐
Miss Ross!
我想跟你私下谈谈
I'd like some private words with you.
我像很多男人般觉得你很吸引
And you I find a sweet distraction, as most men do.
- 恕我们失陪 - 好的 赖比先生
- Will you excuse us? - Of course, Mr La Beef.
你想怎样? 你是谁?
What do you want of me? Who are you?
我寂寂无名 但我前途无限
I'm nobody yet, but I expect to go high.
怎样?
How?
首先 我准备结婚
To begin with, I expect to marry well.
你有合适的发型
You have the haircomb for it.
- 你怎知我是谁 - 昨天见过你妈
- How did you know my name? - I saw your mother yesterday.
你找她有什么事?
What business did you have with her?
这个 你认得照片中的人吗
This. Can you identify the man in this picture?
很像程汤姆 他脸上没有黑斑
That's a likeness of Chaney, with no black mark on his face.
但确是他
But that's him.
你我都在找他 我知道令尊的事
I'm looking for him, and you are, too. I know all about your father.
你昨晚为何不给我看?
Why didn't you show me this last night?
我要按部就班 所以我有两只脚
I only take one step at a time. That's why I was given two feet.
他原名蔡泰龙 在韦科杀了议员
His real name is Theron Chelmsford. He killed a senator in Waco, Texas.
我追踪了他四个月
I've been on his trail almost 4 months.
- 你是执法者? - 德州巡警中士
- You're some kind of law? - I'm a sergeant in the Texas Rangers.
我替该名已故参议员的家人缉凶
I'm working for the family of the late senator.
蔡...或是程...杀了参议员的猎犬
Chelmsford, or Chaney, shot the senator's bird dog.
参议员恐吓要鞭他 程就射死他
The senator threatened to whip him, and Chaney shot him.
别管程了 我旨在把他问吊
Don't worry about Chaney any more. I aim to have him hanged.
警长说你想找人捉拿他
The sheriff told me you were looking for a man to go after him.
我已经找了郭洛达去办
I've already found one for the job, Rooster Cogburn.
他是最棒的副执法官
He's the toughest deputy marshal they have.
或者我加入你和那联邦执法官
Maybe I'll throw in with you and the federal marshal.
- 你要跟他商量 - 对双方有好处
- You'll have to talk to him. - There's mutual advantage.
他熟识地方 我认识程汤姆
He knows the land, and I know Chaney.
至少要两个人才能生擒他
It's at least a two- man job to take him alive.
我要生擒他去德克萨斯州
I must have him alive down to Texas.
不可去德州 要去史密斯堡问吊
We're not taking him back to Texas. We'll take him to Fort Smith to hang.
- 他在哪里问吊很重要吗 - 是的
- Is it important where he hangs? - It is to me.
我也是 韦科有位女士很仰慕我
More so to me. There's a lady in Waco who'd look favourably on me.
在德州行刑也是很重要的
A hanging in Texas would serve just as well.
我要程为我爸服法 不是为猎犬
No! I want Chaney to pay for killing my father, not for some bird dog!
不是为那头狗 是为议员和令尊
It won't be for the dog! It'll be for the senator and your father.
他也会被处死的
He'll be just as dead.
我四个月找不到程可不会出主意
If I couldn't find Chaney in 4 months, I would not advise others how to do it!
较早前我想过偷吻你...
Earlier I thought of stealing a kiss from you,
你虽然又年轻又难应付
although you are very young and unattractive to boot!
但现在我会给你好看的
But now I'd sooner give you some licks with my belt!
尽管放马过来
One would be as unpleasant as the other!
你们德州人不知道我们的厉害
You Texans are ignorant of our ways.
我们不会放过欺负妇孺的男人
We don't go easy on men who abuse women and children.
德州儿童对他们的长辈更加尊重
Texan children show more respect for their elders.
德州人用马刺凿马、发型古怪
Texans gouge their horses with brutal spurs and cultivate their hair like lettuce!
你说得太过分了
You'll push that saucy line too far.
我对你没有好感
I have no regard for you,
我肯定你是自大妄为
but I'm sure you have enough for yourself to go around!
它们全都是出售的
They are all for sale.
除了那四匹瘦小的马
Except those four scrubby ones.
- 是谁的 - 已故罗法伦的继承人
- And... who do they belong to? - The heirs of the late Frank Ross.
我是罗美蒂 我把那些马卖给你
I'm Mattie Ross, and I'd like to sell you back those ponies.
不可以
That's out of the question.
我爸买来作繁殖 但全都是骟马
My father bought them for breeding, but they're all geldings.
- 骟马不能繁殖 - 不关我事
- You cannot breed geldings. - That hardly concerns me.
他用一百元买了四匹小马而已
He bought four ponies for $100, and there's an end of it.
我要替爸收回被偷马匹的三百元
I want $300 for Papa's saddle horse, stolen from your barn.
- 向偷它的人取吧 - 你照顾它的
- Take it up with the man who stole it. - He stole it while it was in your care.
你要负责
You are responsible.
我欣赏你的勇气 但我没有责任
I admire your sand, but... I'm not liable.
- 我会控告你 - 随便你吧
- I will take it to the law. - Do as you think best.
看孤儿寡妇可否获法庭公平对待
We'll see if a widow and three children can get fair treatment in these courts.
- 你告不到的 - 戴格会有办法
- You have no case. - Lawyer Daggett may think otherwise.
- 你很无礼 - 我不想这样的
- You are impudent. - I do not wish to be, sir.
但我不会被人摆布
But I will not be pushed about.
- 我会找我的律师 - 我会找我的
- I'll take it up with my attorney. - And I with mine.
他和我会赚钱 你的律师也会
He and I will make money, and your lawyer will make money.
而你 拍卖商先生 就会赔钱
And you, Mr Auctioneer, will foot the bill!
你是个讨厌鬼
You're a damned nuisance!
你十分钟前说的 谁是著名律师
Who is this famous pleader, of whom I was ignorant 10 minutes ago?
你听过大阿肯色河域高公司吧?
You've heard of the Great Arkansas River Vicksburg and Gulf Company?
我跟域高公司有生意来往
I have done business with the GAV & G, yes.
我的律师迫到他们破产接管
My lawyer forced them into receivership.
他们想跟他作对
They tried to mess with him.
好吧 进来
All right, come inside.
请坐
Sit down.
我愿意给令尊的财产二百元
I will pay a total of $200 to your father's estate
我要一封信说明把我一切债项...
when I have in my hand a letter absolving me of all liability
由始至今全部免除
from the beginning of the world to date!
我要二百元马税加一百元小马费
I want $200 for the horse duty plus another $100 for the ponies.
那些小马不算 我不会买它们
The ponies have no part in this. I won't buy them back.
我会保留小马 茱迪要卖三百元
I'll keep the ponies, and the price for Judy will be $300.
就算是飞马我也不会付那个价钱
I wouldn't pay that for Pegasus! Listen, as I will not bargain further.
我收回小马 令尊的马鞍给两百
I will take the ponies back, keep your father's saddle for $200.
我的律师不想我考虑三百元以下
My lawyer would not wish me to consider anything under $300.
那是所有东西除了马鞍的价钱
That's for everything except the saddle.
我要有书面说明一切价目
I would like to have that in writing, for what it's worth.
我收到它就会汇那笔敲诈的钱
When I have it in my hand, I'll remit the extortion money.
这是你的豁免书 很妥当的了
This is your release. You'll find it in order.
你原来已经写好了
You had that already written out.
- 我会给你一张支票 - 我要现金
- I'll give you a cheque. - I prefer cash.
一百、两百...
One hundred, two hundred...
三百
...three hundred.
你会很快找到人买那些小马的
You'll find a buyer for those ponies very soon.
小石城的制皂厂愿意出每匹十元
I have a tentative offer of $10 a head from the soap works at Little Rock.
把活生生的马肉做成肥皂真可惜
Such a shame to render spirited horseflesh into soap.
- 定能成交 - 我会回来取马鞍
- I'm sure the deal will fall through. - Expect me back for my saddle.
肯定可以
I'm sure I can!
你可认识郭洛达执法官?
Do you know a Marshal Rooster Cogburn?
很多人认识他 有些后悔认识他
Most people know Rooster Cogburn, and some live to regret it.
他是你的亲戚我也不感到惊讶
I wouldn't be surprised to learn he's a relative of yours!
- 早 - 你早
- Morning. - Good morning.
- 郭先生呢 - 睡晚了 昨晚喝醉
- Where's Mr Cogburn? - Sleep late. Very drunk last night.
我没见过没病却十点还在床的人
I've never seen anybody in bed at 10 a.m. Who wasn't sick.
咖啡
Coffee.
他也不是早起的人
You ain't such an early bird yourself!
我差点放弃了你 以为你回家了
I almost gave up on you, figured you'd gone home.
- 你的床要加板条 - 它没有板条
- You need more slats in that bed. - Ain't no slats in it at all.
是中式绳床酷刑装置 我会烧...
Some kind of a Chinese rope bed torture contraption, I'd burn...
你拿到它了 有多少?
You got it! How much is there?
你仍然拼搏?
You still game?
我是天生拼搏 至死不渝
I was born game, and I intend to go out that way.
好 我们今天下午就去抓他
All right, one understanding: We leave this afternoon to get him.
- 你不能去 - 你看错我了
- You're not going! - You misjudge me.
我不能同时对付白和照顾小孩
I can't go up against Pepper's gang, looking after a baby at the same time!
- 我不是小孩 - 没有热饭和暖床
- I'm not a baby. - There's no hot grub or warm beds.
我以前猎浣熊也在外面睡过
I've slept out at night before while hunting coons.
这次不是猎浣熊 不适宜小孩
This ain't no coon- hunt. It's no place for a kid.
- 他们说是猎浣熊 - 你会找妈妈
- They said that about coon- hunting. - You'll be calling for Mama!
我已经不哭了
I've left off crying.
决定吧 若你不够胆我会找别人
Make up your mind. If you're not game, I'll find somebody who is.
我知道你会喝酒 看过你杀老鼠
I know you can drink whisky, and I saw you kill a rat,
其余都是听闻 我不会付钱空谈
but all the rest has been talk, and I'm not paying for talk.
- 我要拍你的臀 - 你怎能那样?
- I ought to paddle your rump! - How do you propose to do that?
若我像你这么臭我不会接近别人
If I smelled as bad as you, I wouldn't live near people!
我已经订了一份简短的协议
I've made up a short agreement between us.
签吧
Sign it.
这里是25元
Here's $25.
出发时再给你25元 成事后50元
I'll give you another $25 when we leave and $50 when the job is done.
我们天亮时可以出发
We can get started at first light.
过河和在印第安人区找个线人
We'll cross the ferry and talk to an informer in the Indian Nation.
他可能有线索
He might know something.
我会作好准备
I'll be more than ready.
将军...
Well, General...
看我们有什么
Look what we got.
有一句古老的谚语
There's an old saw that says:
[一只白脚 买了它」
"One white foot, buy him,"
[两只白脚 试试它」
"two white feet, try him,"
[三只白脚 要偷偷地」
"three white feet, be on the sly,"
[四只白脚 别理它」
"four white feet, pass him by."
但我不同意
But I don't hold with that.
听说有个女孩掉下一口50英尺的井
I just heard that a young girl fell head first into a fifty- foot well.
我还以为是你
I thought perhaps it was you.
不是我
No, it was not I.
那个肥皂商有什么消息?
What do you hear from the soap man?
- 没有 - 我会买其中一匹小马
- Nothing. - I'll take one of the ponies.
那四蹄踏雪黑马 我会叫它小黑
The black one with the white stockings. I'll call him Little Blackie.
- 你给多少钱? - 市价
- What is your offer? - The market price.
那肥皂商给你每匹十元...
The soap man offered you $10 a head...
是整批价 我今早给你每匹25元
That is a lot price. I paid you $25 a head only this morning.
- 那是当时的价 - 告诉我...
- That was the price then. - Tell me this...
你是否打算离开这城?
Do you entertain plans of ever leaving this city?
是 我明早出发去印第安人区
Yes, I'm off early tomorrow morning for the Indian Nation.
郭执法官和我会去抓凶手程汤姆
Marshal Cogburn and I are going after the murderer Tom Chaney.
郭...
Cogburn...
你怎会碰上那滑头的浪子?
How did you light on that greasy vagabond?
他们说他有胆识
They say he has grit.
- 我要个有胆识的人 - 他有的
- I wanted a man with grit. - I suppose he has that.
他恶名昭彰 我可不愿跟他同床
He's a notorious thumper. Not a man I would care to share a bed with.
- 我也不愿 - 我不大信任他
- Nor would I. - I wouldn't trust him too much.
我付了预支 余款事成后再付
I paid a token payment. The balance is paid when the job's done.
这会是一次漫长艰巨的旅程
It may prove to be a long, hard journey.
基督徒不会畏缩这些困难的
A Christian does not flinch from these difficulties.
他也不会找困难 他不是放肆的
Neither does he rashly court them. He is not wilful or presumptuous.
- 你认为我错了? - 你很错
- You think I'm wrong? - I think you are wrong- headed.
我会给12元买那匹马
I'll pay $12 for that pony...
你替我钉蹄铁 我不骑赤脚马
...if you shoe him for me. I will not ride a barefoot pony.
- 你早 - 你早
- Good morning. - Good morning!
你好
Howdy!
- 你来干嘛? - 跟执法官聊天
- What are you doing here? - Having a chat with the marshal.
请坐 妹妹 吃糖吧
Sit down, sis, have some taffy.
这个家伙说他也在追踪同一个人
This jaybird says he's on the track of the same man.
我告诉他我们没兴趣 他跟着我
I told him we're not interested. He's gone behind my back.
一个提着短马枪的人可能有用
A fella that carries a big- bore carbine might come in handy,
若我们被大象或者水牛撞上
if we get jumped by elephants or buffalo!
我们不需要他
We don't need him.
- 准备好了吗 - 只欠好吃的东西
- Everything ready? - All but the grub.
我一定是找错人了
I must have the wrong man.
- 你让女孩摆布你? - 再说一遍
- You let little girls hooraw you? - Mind repeating that, jaybird?
执法官替我工作
The marshal's working for me.
- 她给你多少钱? - 足够的钱
- How much is she paying you? - Enough.
她是否给你五百元?
Is she paying you $500?
不是
No.
若把程定罪德州州长会赏五百元
That's what the Governor of Texas is paying on conviction of Chaney.
五百? 抓杀议员凶手只得这么少
$500? Very little for a man who's killed a senator.
毕斯只是个小参议员
Bibbs was a little senator.
我办妹妹的差事好了
I guess I'll just stick with sis.
毕氏家人另悬红1 500百元抓程
The Bibbs family's put up another $1,500 for Chaney.
- 条件呢 - 只交出程 不论生死
- What are the terms? - Just deliver Chaney, alive or dead.
那较合我意 你会怎样分钱?
That's more to my liking. How will you split up the money?
若生擒分1 500 我要州的五百
If we take him alive, I'll split the $1,500 and keep the state's $500.
若杀死他 我会给你毕家的五百
If we kill him, I'll give you $500 of the Bibbs' money.
我不要把程带返德州
I don't want Chaney taken back to Texas.
- 他要受罚 - 要他为我爸问吊
- He wants him punished, so do you. - I want him to hang for my father.
我不理德州的那些参议员
I don't care about senators in Texas.
你可以亲口告诉他 叫他吃沙
You can tell him to his face. You can make him eat sand.
你可射他的脚 但我们先要抓他
You can shoot him in the foot, but first we gotta catch him!
- 你不能自把自为 - 付了钱就行
- You can't have it all your own way. - I've paid for it so I'll have it my way.
我完全不明白
I don't understand at all.
她不可以去 回家找妈妈吧
She ain't going anyhow. Go home to your mama.
- 我说过她可以去 - 她会惹麻烦
- I told her she could go. - No. She'll make trouble.
独力抓程和领取所有的钱好了
Maybe I'll catch this Chaney by myself and take all the money.
我不会让你得到分文
You might deliver him, but I'd see you didn't collect a thing.
- 你怎做? - 我会争议你的功劳
- How'd you do that? - I'd dispute your claim.
你那样做我会杀死你
Do that, and I'll kill you.
老兄 别小觑你不认识的人
Don't count on shading someone you don't know, fella.
我没见过不能小觑的德州人
I ain't seen no one from Texas I couldn't shade!
你若阻挠我 就不得好死
La Beef, you cross me and you'd think a thousand bricks had fell on you.
你会祈求返回阿拉莫
You'll wish you was back at the Alamo!
打倒他 那笔奖金是赖比的谎话
Knock him down, Rooster! That reward's just La Beef's talk.
我已经给你重酬 他会骗你
I've given you good cash. He'll cheat you!
妹妹 有时要为自己着想一下
A fella's gotta think about himself sometimes, sister.
我们会抓到你要的人 那才重要
We'll get your man, that's the main thing.
把我的25元还给我 拿出来
Give me my $25 back. Hand it over!
我花光了
I spent it.
- 你这个混蛋 - 我会还给你的
- You sorry piece of trash. - I'll get it for you.
你以为骗倒我 你错了
If you think you can cheat me, you're mistaken.
我的律师会找你
You may well hear from my lawyer!
律师? 什么律师?
Lawyer? What lawyer?
别管他 我们管我们的事吧
Don't worry about him. Worry about our business at hand.
- 烈特 - 你早
- Red. - Morning.
- 河水很涨 - 上游一直下雨
- River looks kind of high. - It's been raining up- country.
- 你这次要找谁? - 你会漏风声
- Who are you looking for this time? - If I told you, you might tell him.
你们枪械齐备呢
Well... you're well enough armed.
我会说： [程汤姆 小心」
I'd say, "Tom Chaney, look out!"
你无脑的吗? 你不可以去
Can't you get anything through your head? You're not going!
别理货物了 送我们过河吧
Forget about the freight and take us across.
你不能上船
You're not getting on this ferry!
这是公众地方 我付了一角
This is open to the public. I've paid my 10 cents.
带这个女孩见警长 她是逃犯
Take this girl to the sheriff. She's a runaway.
- 有50元赏金的 - 那是谎话
- There's a $50 reward. - That's a big story!
- 问执法官吧 - 她确是个逃犯
- Ask the marshal. - She's a runaway all right.
- 有通缉令抓她的 - 他们是同党
- Bound to be paper on her. - They're in this together.
我有事要办 你阻我我会告你
I've got business across the river. If you stop me, I'll see you in court!
我有个好律师
I've got a good lawyer.
- 又是戴格 - 她常拿他来唬吓人
- Lawyer Daggett again. - She draws him like a gun!
我不要走上那座山
I will not walk up that hill!
我不会错失五十元的 快上马
I'm not going to let $50 slide. Get on that horse.
等一会
Wait a minute.
我要戴好我的帽
I ought to fix my hat.
我的天
By God!
她令我想起我
She reminds me of me!
那么我们可能相处不来
Then we might just not get along.
你们过河有点慢呢
Well, you were a little slow getting across.
- 你不能去 回去 - 我不要
- I said you weren't going. Go back! - I'll do no such thing!
赖比...
La Beef...
那些马摆脱不到小黑的
Those horses can't get away from Little Blackie.
它们背着胖男人和枪械
They're loaded down with fat men and iron.
现在看你会唱什么歌
Now we'll see what tune you sing!
- 打到你遍体鳞伤 - 有何好处
- I'll raise welts on you like worms! - See what good it does you.
你没有伤到我 我只是生气
You're not hurting me. I'm just mad!
- 你让他这样做 - 不会 放下鞭
- Are you gonna let him do this? - I don't believe I will. Drop the switch!
放下它 你太享受它了
Put it down. You're enjoying it too much.
我要继续
I go ahead with what I start.
你再做就会令你后悔莫及
You do, and it'll be the biggest mistake you ever made!
你一直帮她 但却待她不好
You've taken her part all along, but you ain't doing her no kindness.
别管她
Just leave her alone.
这令我想到一个计划
This has given me a plan.
我们找到程就这样把他打倒
When we locate Chaney, we can jump him this way and knock him out.
然后绑起他 生擒他回去
Then we can tie him up and take him back alive.
- 你们认为如何? - 你不想知的
- What do you think? - You don't want to know what I think.
上马吧
Get on your horse.
还没到晚饭时间?
It's not dinnertime?
这旅程食无定时 上马吧
Dinnertime'll come and go without notice on this trip. Get on your horse.
(伯比杂货店)
长老会的? 南部还是坎伯兰的?
Presbyterian, huh? Southern or Cumberland?
- 南部 - 我家人是坎伯兰的
- Southern. - My folks are Cumberland.
- 我在圣公会长大 - 你是跪拜者
- I was raised in the Episcopal Church. - I figured you for a kneeler!
有什么线索?
What did you learn?
有人见到尼特三天前在麦亚的店
Ned was sighted at McAlester's store about three days ago.
他常到那里见一个荡妇
He goes there from time to time to see a lewd woman.
还有个叫希斯的贼和墨西哥人
A thief named Haze is with him and a Mexican on a round- bellied pony.
程不在 但他有份参与邮车劫案
Chaney wasn't seen, but he was in on that mail hijacking job.
要炖肉吗?
Stew?
- 这路真难行 - 是去麦亚的捷径
- This is worse than a pig trail! - Shortest way to McAlester's.
- 有多远? - 大约六十里
- How far is it? - Around 60 miles.
要走十五天 明天一早出发
We'll make 15 today and get an early start tomorrow.
这次[猎浣熊」你觉得如何?
How do you like this coon- hunt?
不用回望我 我就在这里
Don't be looking around for me. I'll be right here.
你像只走在冰上的猪
You look like a hog on ice!
这个水桶很重
The bucket's heavy.
我比外表坚强
I'm stronger than I look.
- 你带了什么吃的东西? - 盐
- What did you bring to eat? - Salt.
红辣椒
Red pepper.
糖
Taffy.
- 你把这些放在袋里? - 还有...
- Carry those in your pockets? - Yeah. Along with...
子弹和刀子
...cartridges and skinning knife.
- 那些是什么? - 粟米烤饼
- What are those things? - Corn dodgers.
- 你带了多少? - 一定有175个
- How many have you got in there? - It must be 175.
真了不起
I can scarcely credit that.
陈利一定以为有很多执法官
Chen Lee must've thought it was for a wagonload of marshals.
味道像铁一样
That tastes like iron.
这么容易拿到水你们真走运
You're lucky to be where water's so handy.
我曾经喝过很脏的水 也算好运
I've drunk out of a filthy hoofprint, and I was glad to get it.
若我遇上一个不喝脏水的德州人
If ever I meet one of you Texans who ain't drunk from a hoofprint,
我会跟他握手或请他抽雪茄
I'll shake their hand or buy them a Daniel Webster cigar!
你们被绑在绵羊背上多久了?
How long you boys down there been mounted on sheep?
你尽管说笑话吧 但我告诉你...
Have your little joke, but I'll tell you one thing:
你的马倒下时那小家伙仍在奔跑
That little fella'll still be running when your big stud is collapsed.
绵羊
Sheep!
我们不想被发现 火堆太大了
That fire's a little big if we're going to pass unnoticed.
护林条例是要生小火
Small fire is Ranger policy.
我有个主意
Listen, I have an idea.
我给你们讲午夜访客的故事
I'll tell you the story of the Midnight Caller.
你们一个扮访客 我教你说什么
One of you plays the caller, I'll tell you what to say,
我会扮演其他角色
and I'll play all the other parts.
好的 说吧
Fine. Go ahead and tell it.
- 你停止喝酒我才说 - 算了吧
- I'll tell it if you stop drinking. - Let it go.
小妹妹 没有交易
That, baby sister, is no trade.
至少小黑喜欢那些粟米烤饼
At least Little Blackie likes the corn dodgers.
是它们的咸味
It's the salt in them.
我们入夜前去不到麦亚了
We won't get to McAlester's by dark.
我们还是去一个我熟识的地方吧
We'd better head for an empty dugout I know.
- 可以吃你的火鸡 - 怎吃? 烂的
- We can eat your turkey there. - How? It's all ripped up.
对 稀巴烂
Yeah, pretty chewed.
中了太多枪
Too much gun!
我以为你说这里无人的
I thought you said it would be empty.
你们是谁? 你们想怎么样?
Who are you? What do you want?
- 我们想找地方睡觉 - 没有房间
- We're looking for a place to sleep. - There's no room for you here.
试试放在烟囱上
Try that on the chimney.
我是联邦人员 谁在里面
I'm a federal officer! Speak up, who's in there?
不关你事 快走
None of your damn business. Keep riding!
- 是关艾民吗 - 我们不认识此人
- Is that Emmett Quincy? - We don't know Emmett Quincy.
艾民 是洛达 这里还有五个人
Emmett, this is Rooster! I got five more marshals out here.
- 我们有一桶煤油 - 喝它吧
- We got a bucket of coal oil! - Drink it!
再过一分钟你就要喝它
One more minute and you're gonna drink it!
把枪抛出来 你们高举双手出来
Chuck your guns out and follow them with your hands high!
若煤油流进烟囱 所有人都会死
If that coal oil goes down the chimney, we'll kill everyone that comes out!
外面没有五个人
There's no five marshals out there.
- 别冒险 - 阿蒙中枪 不能走路
- Don't you bet your life on it! - Moon can't walk, he's hit.
- 拉他出来 - 你有何令状抓我?
- Drag him out. - What papers you got on me?
我没有令状要抓你 快出来
I got no papers on you. You better move!
叫那些人小心用枪 我们出来了
Tell those others to be careful with their guns. We're coming out!
伏下
Hit the dirt! Belly down!
张开手脚
Spreadeagle!
我忘了它们在那里
I forgot they were there.
你们进去
Get inside, both of you.
用这个擦你的腿
Wrap that around your leg.
把马匹带去棚屋
Put the horses in the lean- to.
- 给他们扣上手铐 - 起来
- Cuff them. - Get up.
坐下 去那边
Sit down. Get down there.
你们太易受惊了
You fellas are way too jumpy.
你们除了偷牲畜还做过什么?
What have you been up to, besides stealing stock?
- 你没有缉拿令 - 但我有些原告
- You ain't got no papers on us. - No, but I got some John Does.
反抗联邦人员要坐牢一年
Resisting a federal officer, that's a year right there!
- 我的腿很痛 - 肯定是的
- My leg hurts! - I bet it does, sonny boy.
你坐着别动就不会流这么多血
You sit still so it won't bleed so bad.
- 你几时见过白 - 我不认识白
- When did you last see Pepper? - I don't remember any Pepper.
矮小、烦躁、紧张...下唇受伤
Short, feisty fella, nervous, with a messed- up lower lip.
记不起 有古怪口唇的?
That don't bring nobody to mind. A funny lip?
不是一直那样 是我射伤他的
It wasn't always like that. I shot him in it.
下唇? 你瞄准什么来射?
The lower lip? What was you aiming at?
他的上唇
His upper lip!
尼特有个新手下 脸上有黑斑的
Ned's got a new boy with him, a black mark on his face.
我也没有印像
That don't bring nobody to mind either.
- 你什么都不知 - 我知也不会说
- You don't know anything, do you? - If I did, I wouldn't blow.
你又怎么样?
How about you?
若不伤害朋友 我会协助执法的
I always help the law, if it don't harm my friends.
好 否则我会在史密斯堡告发你
Pretty good idea, otherwise I'll turn you in at Fort Smith.
那时你的腿会肿得比帽带还要紧
By that time your leg'll be swollen up tighter than Dick's hatband!
坏死了他们就会把它切除
Mortified and they'll cut it off.
你活得到我就要你坐三、四年牢
If you live, I'll get you 3 or 4 years in a penitentiary.
- 想欺压我 - 我会带你去找麦亚
- You're trying to get at me. - If you talk, I'll take you to McAlester's.
会替你取出子弹 我会给你...
They'll get that ball out of your leg, and I'll give you...
两、三天时间离开这里
...2 or 3 days to get out of the territory.
阿蒙 由我来说
Moon, I'll do the talking!
听他说 不然失掉你的腿或没命
Listen to him, you'll lose your leg or your life.
- 关没有受伤 - 他没有缉捕令
- Quincy ain't hurting. - He ain't got nothing on us.
- 看过了 有六匹马 - 什么种类
- Been looking around. Six horses. - What kind of horses?
很好的 全都有马蹄铁
Right good mounts. All shod.
- 他们在等人 - 还用你说
- They're waiting for somebody. - You don't say!
你们不说就干活 切好拿去煮
If you won't talk, you can keep busy. Cut that up for frying.
你看什么? 你是谁?
What are you looking at? Who are you?
我是耶路县的罗美蒂
I'm Mattie Ross of Yell County.
她在这里干嘛?
What's she doing here?
她在追捕她的杀父仇人
She's after the man that killed her father.
他姓程 是酒鬼 醉酒令他杀人
His name is Chaney, a whisky drinker like you. It led to killing in the end.
回答吧 他和我的律师会帮你
Answer the marshal's questions, he'll help you. My lawyer'll help, too.
阿蒙 别和这些人唠叨
Don't jaw with these people, Moon.
- 我不喜欢你 - 你跟我说话吗?
- I don't like the way you look. - Talking to me, runt?
我不喜欢你切火鸡的方法
And I don't like the way you're cutting up that turkey.
- 他乱切 - 做好点 否则你吃毛
- He's making a mess of that turkey! - Do it right, or you'll eat the feathers.
我希望你去坐牢
I hope you go to jail.
阿蒙失去他的腿真可惜
Shame a kid like Moon losing his leg.
这么年轻就要靠支架走路
Too young to be hopping around on a willow peg.
他太喜爱跳舞和运动了
Loves to dance too much and sports.
- 你又想欺压我 - 快说实情
- You're trying to get at me again. - With the truth!
- 两天前见过尼特 - 我会杀你
- We saw Ned two days ago... - You go on, I'll kill you!
关 我要去看医生 我会说出来
Quincy, I got to have a doctor. I'll tell what I know.
天 我会死的 救我
Lord, I'm gonna die! Help me.
我帮不到你什么
I can't do a thing for you.
你的同伴杀你的 我已对付了他
Your partner's killed you, and I've done for him.
- 别让狼吃我 - 我会把你埋掉
- Don't let the wolves get me! - I'll see you get buried.
白尼特在哪里?
Where's Ned Pepper?
他们劫基蒂快车前会来配备马匹
They're gonna rob the Katy Flyer. They're coming here for remounts.
可有看见一个脸上有枪伤的人?
See a fella with a powder burn on his face?
没有 我的哥哥...
No. My brother...
是德州奥斯丁循道会牧师葛佐治
...George Garrett, Methodist circuit rider out of Austin, Texas.
白尼特几时到达?
When's Pepper due here?
卖掉我的东西 把钱寄给我哥哥
Sell my traps and send the money to my brother.
可要我们告诉他发生了什么事?
Shall we tell your brother what happened?
不要紧 他知道的
It doesn't matter. He knows.
我日后会和他在光荣大道上同行
I'll meet him later, walking the streets of glory.
别期望在那里见到关
Don't expect to see Quincy there.
关?
Quincy?
他从没待薄我 直至他杀了我
He never played me false until he killed me.
给我喝点冻水
Let me have a cool drink of water.
我感觉到手指仍在那里
It felt as though I still had fingers there.
给我
Let me have that.
- 是爸的其中一枚金币 - 真的?
- It's one of Papa's gold pieces. - You sure?
在加州铸造的 价值超过36元
It was minted in California. It's worth over $36.
爷爷在爸结婚时送给他的
Grandpa gave Papa two when he married.
- 找到程的行踪 - 至少找到白
- Looks like we're on Chaney's trail. - At least we're on Ned's.
把手铐的钥匙给我 去装好马鞍
Gimme the key to these cuffs. Now go saddle the horses.
阿蒙说他们会来 你想逃走?
Moon said they were coming here. You aim to run?
我要做我此行的目的 快装马鞍
I aim to do what I came here to do. Saddle the horses.
收拾好地方
Straighten up the place.
带你的马去那边找个阵地
Take your horse and find a position over there.
我在这边 我开火时你才可开枪
I'll be on this side. Don't shoot unless I do.
我们要他们入那间屋里
We want them in that dugout.
我会射最后一个人 然后抓他们
I'll shoot the last man in the door and we'll have them.
- 不警告就射? - 让他知道厉害
- You'll shoot him without a call? - Then he'll know we're serious.
之后我会叫 看可有人肯被生擒
I'll holler down after I shoot, see if anyone wants to be taken alive.
他们不肯我们就开枪
But when they won't, we'll shoot them!
- 我要活捉程 - 德州州长也要
- I want Chaney alive. - So does the Governor of Texas.
他们人多势众 我们只有两个人
All I know is there's a lot of them and only two of us.
不如我在程入屋前制伏他
Why don't I nick Chaney before he gets inside?
入屋前就开火 他们会四散的
Any shooting before they get inside, and they'll break.
我们会空手而回
We're apt to come up with an empty sack.
若他们四散 我会对付程
All right, but if they break, I'll nick Chaney.
若你用你的枪射中程 他会死的
If you hit Chaney with your rifle, you'll kill him!
- 记得那只火鸡吗? - 对
- Remember the turkey! - Yeah.
你去追尼特 我会对付程
You go after Ned, I'll take care of Chaney.
- 他怎样的? - 矮、烦躁、多言
- What does Ned look like? - Short, feisty, doing all the talking.
- 她去哪里? - 我跟郭洛达
- Where does she go? - I go where Rooster goes.
别走开 让马匹保持安静
Stay here and keep the horses quiet.
- 我在那边看不见 - 今天看够了
- I can't see anything from over there. - You've seen enough killing today.
我不要独自一人 我去拿我的枪
I'm not staying by myself. Wait, I'll get my revolver.
为什么?
What for?
让你可以射掉自己的脚?
So you can shoot your own foot off?
为何你留空一个弹膛?
Why do you keep that one chamber empty?
让我不会射掉我的脚
So I won't shoot my foot off!
- 吃烤饼吗 - 点火柴让我看看它
- Corn dodger? - Light a match and let me see it first.
- 为什么? - 有些上面有血迹
- What for? - Some have got blood on them.
我们不能点火柴
We ain't lighting no matches.
我不吃了
I don't want any.
你以前是做什么的
What did you do before this?
什么都做过...除了打理学校
Just about everything... except keep school.
- 你怎样失去眼睛的? - 打仗
- How did you lose your eye? - It was in the war.
孤独杰克队 堪萨斯城外的纷争
The Lone Jack, a scrap outside Kansas City.
战后你做过什么?
What did you do after the war?
打劫出纳员 去伊利诺州买餐馆
I robbed a paymaster, went to Illinois and bought an eating place,
娶了个离婚女人
married a grass widow.
那餐馆有张桌球台
The place had a billiard table.
- 你没说过有太太 - 我们不长久
- You never told me you had a wife. - I didn't have her long.
我的朋友都是一班流氓
My friends were a pack of river rats,
她不喜欢他们的圈子
and she didn't crave their society.
她离去重投在帕多卡的首任丈夫
She upped and left me and went back to her first husband in Paducah.
她说： [再见 洛达 你不得体」
"Goodbye, Reuben," she says, "the love of decency ain't in you."
一个离婚女人竟和你谈体面
That's a divorced woman talking for you about decency.
我对她说： [再见 诺拉」
I told her, "Goodbye, Nola."
[但愿那混蛋这次令你快乐」
"I hope that bastard makes you happy this time."
你们有没有儿女?
Did you have any children?
有一个儿子 诺拉把他带走了
There was a boy, Nola took him with her.
反正他从不喜欢我
He never liked me anyway.
学礼是个笨拙的孩子
A clumsier child you'll never see than Horace.
我肯定他打破了四十只杯子
I bet he broke forty cups!
你不后悔偷了那笔钱?
Never did get you for stealing that money?
- 那不算是偷 - 它不属于你
- I didn't consider it stealing. - It didn't belong to you.
我需要路费 那新墨西哥的银行
I needed a road stake. Like that bank in New Mexico.
我需要路费 它就在那里
I needed a road stake, and there it was.
我从没打劫市民或抢人的手表
I never robbed no citizen or took a man's watch!
都是偷窃
It's all stealing.
新墨西哥人认为是 我要逃命
That's the position those New Mexicans took. I had to flee for my life!
宝是匹好马 没有马追得到它
Bo was a young colt then, no horse could run him into the ground.
那班人追不上时...
When that posse thinned out,
我把宝调头 我咬着缰绳...
I turned Bo around and, taking the reins in my teeth,
手执双枪向那班人开火
charged them boys firing two Navy Sixes.
他们一定是爱家的已婚男人
They must have been married men who loved their families,
因为他们四散逃回家
'cause they scattered and ran for home!
你没有家人 只有陈利和那只猫
You don't have any family, do you? Except Chen Lee and that lazy cat.
优秀将军不是我的 猫不属于人
General Price don't belong to me. Cats don't belong to nobody!
它只跟我同住 我当然依赖它...
He just rooms with me. Course I depend on him...
好...
Well...
小妹妹 你还是睡觉吧
Baby sister, you better try and get some sleep.
他们到来时我会叫醒你
I'll wake you up when they get here.
嘘
Shh!
看来阿蒙说的是真话
Looks like Moon was telling the truth.
- 他们在做什么? - 到处探查
- What are they doing? - Smelling around.
看到程吗?
You see Chaney?
我看不清楚他们的脸
I can't make out their faces.
那个人是白尼特
That's Ned Pepper, all right.
关 阿蒙
Quincy! Moon!
在大叫的正是他
That's him hollering.
跟他一起的是墨西哥人阿博
That's the original Mexican Bob with him.
- 多过一个人吗 - 有个年轻人
- There's more than one? - There's a younger one.
但他不是这帮人的一分子
But he ain't a patch to this one.
阿蒙
Moon!
关
Quincy!
他坏了事情
Now he's done it!
尼特 这边
Over here, Ned!
我中枪了
I'm hit.
叫他[好运」白尼特并非无因
They don't call him Lucky Ned Pepper for nothing.
那人为他牺牲性命 他头也不回
That man gave his life for him. He didn't even look back.
回头是个坏习惯
Looking back is a bad habit.
好...
Well...
你有什么解释?
What's your story?
我在转移阵地 听到第一响枪声
I was on the move to a better place, and I heard the first shot.
睡着了才是吧
More likely asleep!
- 认识他们吗 - 在沙咀的是希斯
- You know who they are? - The one on the sand spit's Haze.
这个孩子? 我不认识
The boy? I don't know.
他比我大不了多少
He's not much older than I am.
只是擦伤一点罢了
That's nothing but a little scratch.
不关你的事 给我们煮咖啡吧
That's nothing to do with you. Go make us some coffee!
- 不会很久的 - 别管它 进去
- It won't take long. - Let it go and go on inside!
你为什么这么笨?
Why are you being so foolish?
- 你是射马高手 - 我想射白尼特
- You're quite a horse- shooter. - I was trying for Ned Pepper.
下次瞄准马就可能射中白的了
Next time try for the horse and maybe you'll hit Pepper!
你在等什么? 我们去追他们吧
What are we waiting for? Let's ride after them.
不 我知道他们要去哪里
I say no. I know where they're going to earth.
你看着他们跑掉是抓不到人的
You can't take men by watching them run away.
我熟识这个国家和这些人
I know this country, and I know these men.
我们带马匹和死者去麦亚那里
We'll take the horses and the dead into McAlester,
我会领取铁路局发出的赏金
and I'll put in a claim for any reward the railroad may offer.
- 你同意吗? - 暂时吧
- You backed up? - Some... for now.
- 诅咒口哨者 - 他不要想着手伤
- Damn a man that whistles! - He's keeping his mind off his hand.
你不关心我的 是吗?
You don't think very much of me, do you?
若你安静我就完全不想你
I don't think about you at all, if you keep quiet.
听说你跟昆齐和边境那班人一起
I was told that you rode with Quantrell and that border trash.
听说昆齐他们不是士兵 是土匪
I heard Quantrell and his men weren't soldiers but murdering thieves.
我也听说过
I heard the same thing.
听说他们杀害妇孺
I heard they murdered women and children.
我也听说过 那是谎话
I heard that, too, and it's a damn lie.
战时你是哪一派的?
What outfit were you with during the war?
- 史寇比萨堡 - 我指你支持哪方
- Shreveport, with Kirby Smith. - I mean what side were you on?
我跟从史寇比将军服役
I served with General Kirby Smith.
我感到很光荣
I don't have to hang my head when I say it.
来吧 让我在她面前出丑吧
Go ahead, make me look foolish in her eyes.
你不需要我这样做
You don't need me for that.
我不喜欢你说话的态度
I don't like the way you make conversation.
我不喜欢你说昆齐队长的话
I don't like your conversation about Captain Quantrell.
队长? 什么队长? 一群土匪?
Captain? Captain of what? A bunch of thieves?
小伙子 若你想找麻烦 我奉陪
Young fella, if you're looking for trouble, I'll accommodate you.
否则...别多管闲事
Otherwise... leave it alone.
我在想着白尼特
I've been thinking about Pepper.
可能他杀了那两个人
Maybe he'd have murdered those two so they wouldn't inform on him.
- 尼特不会那样做 - 为什么?
- Ned wouldn't do that. - Why not?
他不会无故杀人
He doesn't kill people for no reason.
他有理由才会杀他们
Had he a reason, he'd kill them.
看来我们有些旅客很疲累了
Looks like we might joggle some of our passengers off.
他们没事的
Well, they're past hurting.
- 我们停在此好吗 - 好 很多人
- We'll tie up here, if you don't mind? - Sure, marshal, you've quite a load.
是 有一半人是我想找的
Yeah... about half the load I was looking for.
进去找麦太太吧 她会弄晚饭
Go in and meet Mrs McAlester, she'll fix some dinner.
- 我去跟和平人员谈 - 我也去
- I want a word with the peace officer. - I'll go, too.
我去叫太太给你们弄饭
I'll tell the wife to fix something for all of you.
去请麦太太帮你包扎吧
You go inside, maybe Mrs McAlester can fix that poor little hand of yours!
我的手没事
My poor little hand can keep.
洛达 你来这里干什么?
Rooster! What are you doing here?
布斯、贾柏高
Boots! Gaspargo!
你让印第安人在身后拿着剃刀?
You're letting that Indian behind you with a blade?
- 我是印第安人 - 有很多战利品
- 'Cause I'm an Indian. - Plenty of scalps on Indian belts!
你们要追白尼特 来这里就错了
If you're after Ned Pepper, you're on a cold trail here.
我们也在找人 脸上有黑斑的
We're looking for another man, too. Black mark on his face.
- 他跟白一路的 - 他是德州官员
- We think he's running with Ned. - That's a Texan peace officer!
尼特两天前路经这里
Ned passed through a couple of days ago.
只有他 希斯和墨西哥人阿博
Him, Haze, Mexican Bob. Only those three were seen.
- 我知他躲在哪里 - 要大量人马
- I know where Ned's holed up. - You'll need 100 marshals to get him!
我是耶路县的罗美蒂
My name is Mattie Ross from Yell County.
那个有黑斑姓程的人杀了我父亲
That man with the black mark killed my father. He's called Chaney.
希斯、阿博、关和小子在外面
I got Haze and some youngster outside with Moon and Quincy.
你们替我埋藏他们 我要赶路
I want you to bury 'em for me. I'm in a hurry.
他们死了?
They're dead?
不然我不会叫你埋藏他们
I wouldn't want you to bury them if they weren't!
- 赖比的手怎样 - 我也是好医生
- What about La Beef's hand? - Gaspargo's a good doctor, too.
- 去把它弄好 - 它可以等
- Take care of it. - It can wait.
- 残废就没用 - 复完也不大有用
- You're no good use if handicapped. - And small use if he ain't!
- 先去洗手 - 为什么?
- Wash first. - Why?
- 你吃饭前不洗手吗 - 又不吃手
- Don't you wash before you eat? - Ain't gonna eat his hand.
- 你不知道有细菌吗? - 不知道
- Don't you know about germs? - No...
去吧 你输了
Go wash, Gaspargo. You lost!
这是阿蒙
That's Moon.
关
Quincy.
希斯 他第一次中枪
Haze! First time he ever stayed shot!
这是韦比利 来自一个好家庭
I know this boy. Billy Walsh. Comes from a good family.
替比利家人留下尸体 其余埋葬
Hold good Billy for his folks and bury the rest of them.
我会张贴姓名让要他们的人来掘
I'll post their names. If anyone wants them, they can dig them up.
卖他们的衣物马匹然后分钱给你
Sell their horses, coats, guns and saddles, and I'll split it with you.
你对阿蒙说你会寄钱给他哥哥
You told Moon you'd send money to his brother.
- 忘了寄去哪里 - 奥斯丁循道会
- I forget where to send it. - The Methodist church, Austin.
你肯定是奥斯丁不是达拉斯?
Are you sure it was Austin and not Dallas?
你知道是奥斯丁
You know it was Austin!
把它写给队长吧
Write it out for the captain.
寄十元给这个人 说他被葬在此
Boots, send this man $10 and tell him he's buried here.
好的 这个人射中白尼特的马?
I'll do that. So this man shot Ned Pepper's horse?
对 他是埃尔帕索有名的马杀手
Yeah, this is the famous horse- killer from El Paso!
他相信各人作准备 就不会捣乱
He believes in putting everybody afoot. Less mischief that way.
少一些马就少一些马贼
Fewer horses, fewer horse- thieves!
你的手怎么样?
How's your hand?
枪和手都准备再发射
Both rifle and hand are ready to shoot again.
希望射得比从前直吧
Straighter than before, I hope!
小妹妹
Well, sister!
我是时候赶路了
The time has come for me to ride hard and fast.
你留在麦家 我很快会带程回来
You stay here with the McAlesters, and I'll be back soon with Chaney.
- 你不能丢下我 - 她走了这么远
- You can't get shed of me. - She's come this far.
- 够远了 - 我不会临阵退缩
- It's far enough. - I won't quit when we're so close.
她说得有理 她很有胆识
There's something in what she's saying. She's won her spurs.
说 我说了
Let it go. I've said my piece.
- 别再说什么胆识了 - 我要去
- No more talk of "winning spurs"! - I'm going.
不是因为你说我可不可以去
Not because you say I can or can't.
我付了钱来这里 我要做我的事
I paid good money to be here, and I'm on my own business.
我们别再争论了
We'll have no more talk about it!
吃饭吧
Let's eat!
你在干什么?
What are you doing?
找蛛丝马迹
Looking for a sign.
你看到它也等于看不到
You couldn't see it if you saw it!
我们步行一段路
We'll walk a ways.
你又在找蛛丝马迹?
You looking for a sign again?
是宝
It was Bo.
它的脚步乱了
He put his foot wrong.
它很疲倦
He's tired.
这不是斜坡
This is no grade.
我搬着铁炉上过更斜的坡
I've freighted iron stoves up harder grades than this.
我们在这里扎营
We'll camp here.
这里
Here...
我在科罗拉多搬运时擅长用拉绳
I was a pretty fair hand with a jerk- line when I was freighting in Colorado.
当时我替一个责任心重的人打工
I worked for a fella that was always down with something.
他体内怀着20英尺的绦虫也要工作
He was carrying a 21 - foot tapeworm with his business responsibilities.
它令他衰老 他老婆接掌生意
That aged him! His wife commenced running things.
我告诉她我不想替她打工
I wasn't about to work for her, so I told her so.
女人并不慷慨
Women have no generosity.
天 她们很吝啬
Lord God, how they hate to pay up!
男人绝不打女人工 除非是蠢材
A man will never work for a woman unless he's got clabber for brains!
我给你的25元又怎样?
What about the $25 I paid you?
什么25元?
What $25?
我不会跟醉酒鬼斗嘴
I will not bandy words with a drunkard!
聪明 你赢了个笨蛋也没出色
That's real smart. You've done nothing when you've bested a fool.
我们离开家 差不多走了五十里
We have come nearly 50 miles from McAlester's.
很接近白尼特的营地了
We're close to Ned Pepper's camp.
明天我们会抓他
Tomorrow we'll take him.
若我们像你说的接近就不该生火
If we're as close as you say, I don't think you should make a fire.
没有人叫你做
Nobody asked you.
你拿水壶去哪里?
Where are you going with that canteen?
去洗脸
Wash the sleep off me.
我们没有水了 喝了它吧
We got no water to spare for that. Just take a drink!
下面有一条小溪
I'd say there's a stream down below.
你去洗脸就没早餐吃?
You wash and you'll get no breakfast!
我们不会浪费时间
We'll waste no more time.
我们其中一个要陪她去吗?
Shouldn't one of us go down with her?
可能会不安全
It might not be safe.
她比她遇上的东西更安全...
It's safer for her than whatever she meets...
男人或者野兽
...man or beast!
我认得你 小掌柜美蒂
I know you. Little Mattie, the bookkeeper.
我也认得你 程汤姆
And I know you, Tom Chaney.
你干什么? 这里没有钱给你扣除
What are you doing? There's no money for you to squeeze here.
- 我来取水 - 我不是这个意思
- I came to fetch water. - That was not my meaning.
我要带你回史密斯堡问吊
I'm here to take you back to Fort Smith and hang you.
我不会去 那又怎样?
I won't go. How do you like that?
山上有一队官员会逼你去
There's a posse of officers up the hill that'll force you to go.
- 有多少人? - 50 他们认真的
- How many officers? - I'd say 50, and they mean business.
你快给我上山
So you just walk right in front of me up that hill.
我要劳驾那些官员来追我了
I think I'll oblige those officers to come after me.
若你拒绝我就会开枪射你
If you refuse, I'll have to shoot you.
是吗?
Is that so?
你要扣扳机的
You'd better cock your piece.
拉后 直至锁着
All the way back until it locks.
我懂得怎么做
I know how to do it.
你说不会自愿跟我走吧?
You're saying you won't go with me of your own free will?
你说错了 是你跟我走
You just got it the other way around. Now you follow me!
- 我以为你不会做的 - 妹妹
- I didn't think you'd do it. - Sis!
- 你在哪里 - 在下面 我抓到程
- Where are you? - I'm down here. I got Chaney!
我以为你不会做的
I just didn't think you'd do it!
我有条肋骨折断了
One of my short ribs is broken!
我父亲救你时你杀了他
You killed my father, when he was trying to help you.
你是个混蛋
You're just a piece of trash.
你还杀了个坐在门廊的德州议员
You also killed a senator in Texas, when he was sitting on a porch swing.
一切冲着来的 现在被小孩射中
Everything happens to me. And now I'm shot by a child!
你不起来我就再射你
I'll shoot you again if you don't get up!
我父亲在你挨饿时收容你
My father took you in when you were hungry.
小丫头 我要狠狠的教训你
Little busybody! I'll teach you a lesson you'll never forget.
妹妹
Sis! Sis!
快点 下面这里
Hurry up! Down here!
快带她走
Take her and go!
带马上山 别停留
Up the hill with the horses and don't stop!
那边的人是谁?
Who holds out there?
郭洛达执法官和五十个持械人员
Marshal Rooster Cogburn and fifty other armed officers.
你再撒谎我就轰掉你的头
Tell me another lie and I'll stove in your head!
快说 那边的人是谁?
The truth! Who's out there?
郭洛达执法官和一个德州巡警
Marshal Rooster Cogburn and a Texas Ranger.
洛达
Rooster!
洛达 你听到我吗?
Rooster, can you hear me?
你快回应否则我杀死这女孩
You better answer or I'll kill this girl! You know I'll do it!
你想我杀死她?
You want me to kill her?
尼特 你要做就做吧
Do what you think is best, Ned!
干嘛 你...
Why, you...
她对我没有用 只是个逃犯
She's nothing to me! Nothing but a runaway!
你和那个巡警要马上走
You and that ranger get moving double fast!
我看见你们在北面山上就放过她
If I see you riding over that north ridge, I'll spare the girl.
你们有五分钟
You got five minutes!
- 我要多过五分钟 - 不行
- We'll need more than five minutes. - I won't give you any more.
有队执法官快到达
There'll be a party of marshals coming soon.
你交程汤姆给我 我会拖延他们
You give me Tom Chaney, and I'll mislead them for six hours.
还要放走那女孩
Throw in that spitfire of a girl, too.
太不可信了
Too thin, Rooster, too thin!
我不会相信你的
I won't trust you.
你的五分钟快完了 走吧
Your five minutes are running. You better move!
我们走 但我们要多过五分钟
All right, we're moving, but we need more than five minutes.
我没打过女人或小孩 但我会做
I never busted a cap on a woman or nobody under sixteen. But I'll do it.
我是耶路县的罗美蒂
I'm Mattie Ross of Yell County.
我家有产业 为何要这样对我?
My family has property. Why am I being treated like this?
你知道我要做什么就够了
Well, it's enough that you know I'll do what I have to do.
我看见你中枪 你的伤口呢?
I saw you shot. Where are your wounds?
我的伤口在里面愈合
My wounds heal by themselves from inside.
你和夏路留下来监视着下面
You and Harold stay here, keep a watch out below.
叫只火鸡静点 否则我宰了它
Keep this turkeycock quiet or we'll have him for supper.
你干嘛不闭嘴?
Why don't you shut up? !
他是不是低能的?
Is he simple- minded?
他们都很蠢 夏路最糟
They're all touched, but Harold's the worst.
他们的妈和兄最蠢 但是神枪手
No, their ma's the worst, then his brother. But they're all good shots.
伏下
Get down!
我会扭断你条瘦颈
I'll wring your scrawny neck!
不 去给马匹装马鞍
No, you won't. Go and get those horses saddled!
去帮他 你坐着别动
Lend him a hand. You sit there and be still.
你的五分钟完了 他们最好出现
Your five minutes is up, they better show.
- 你在干嘛 - 程杀死了我父亲
- What are you doing here? - Chaney shot my father to death.
人家说郭洛达很有胆识
I was told Rooster Cogburn has grit.
我雇用他追凶手 我要亲自射他
I hired him to go after the murderer. I shot him myself.
他死了就不会这样 我的枪走火
If I'd killed him, I wouldn't be in this fix. My gun misfired.
他们会做的
Well, they will do it.
女孩都爱漂亮 你却喜欢枪
Most girls like to play pretties, but you like guns.
我喜欢就要一支有用的
If I did, I'd have one that worked.
我会给他们多一点时间
I'll give them a little more time.
- 昨晚洛达是否伏击我们? - 是
- Did Rooster waylay us last night? - Yes.
- 他杀死关和阿蒙? - 他们死了
- Did he take Quincy and Moon? - They're both dead.
很可怕的 你要好律师吗?
It was terrible to see. Do you need a good lawyer?
我要个好法官
I need a good judge.
希斯也死了 还有那救你的男孩
That man called Haze, he's dead, too. And the boy that saved your life.
我很感激他 但他该当心点
I'm happy he did what he did, but he should've looked out for himself.
这适用于你的好朋友洛达
That goes for your good friend, Rooster.
尼特
Hey, Ned!
郭洛达不是我的好朋友
Rooster Cogburn is no good friend of mine.
他是个酒鬼 笨蛋
He's a drunken, gabbing fool.
他领我们落在你手上 还丢下我
He led us right into your hands and left me with a gang of cut- throats.
在史密斯堡他们叫这做胆识?
They call that grit in Fort Smith?
我们在耶路县叫它做别的东西
We call it something else in Yell County.
我被其中一个官员伏击
I was shot from ambush by one of those officers.
你怎可以这样说谎?
How can you tell a big story like that?
我们有五人四马 程留下来
We're five men and four horses. Chaney stays. You lost the horse.
我会派人带一匹马来接你
I'll send someone to get you with a fresh mount.
我不要跟程在一起
I'm not staying with Chaney.
他不会伤害你的 知道吗?
He won't harm you. Understand?
洛达给我们六小时保她平安
Rooster gave us six hours if we keep her safe. If you don't...
否则你拿不到钱
...you don't get paid!
- 费诺 让我上马 - 不
- Let me ride with you, Farrell. - No!
- 你呢 阿博? - 不行
- How about you, Bob? - No!
夏路?
- Harold? - Cock- a- doodle- doo!
- 再来 - 扮山羊叫
- Do it again, Harold! Do a goat! - Baa! Baa!
今晚在莫那里见吧
We'll see you tonight at Maw's.
- 你干什么? - 我要取水洗手
- What are you doing? - I'm getting water to wash my hands.
一点污迹伤不到你的
A little smut won't hurt you.
对 否则你们也死了
True. Or else you lot would surely be dead!
别激怒我
Don't provoke me.
那个洞有响尾蛇 我会抛你下去
There's rattlesnakes in that pit, and I'll throw you in it!
白尼特说若你骚扰我就不给你钱
Ned Pepper said if you molest me, he'll not pay you. He's your boss.
他不会给我的 他早知我会被捕
He's no idea of paying me. He left me knowing I'd be caught.
你放我走我两天都不会供你出来
If you let me go now, I'll keep silent about you for two days.
我可以令你永远闭嘴
I can do better. I can shut you up forever!
程 够了
All right, Chaney. That's enough.
举起双手
Get your hands up.
- 去那边 - 一切都不利于我
- Get over there. - Everything's against me.
你有受伤吗 受伤的是我
- You hurt, Mattie? - I'm the one that's hurt!
- 洛达呢? - 在下面一个地方
- Where's Rooster? - Below, in a place we can watch.
- 小黑呢? - 洛达带着它
- Where's Little Blackie? - Rooster's got him.
过去那边别动
Get over there and stay over there.
小心 他说那个洞有蛇
Watch out, he said there are snakes in that hole.
那女孩在哪里?
Where's the girl?
刚才还是平安 现在我可不知道
In wonderful health the last I saw her. I don't know now.
快说 她在哪里?
Answer for her now. Where is she?
洛达 快走
Rooster! Make a run for it!
我找到美蒂和程了
I got Mattie. Chaney, too!
可否让路? 我在别处有事要办
Will you give us the road? I have business elsewhere.
费诺 你和你的兄弟站开
Farrell, you and your brother stand clear.
我今天对你们没兴趣 站开
I got no interest in you today. Stand clear, you won't get hurt.
喔...
Cock- a- doodle- doo!
你认为以一对四便算扯平?
You think one on four's a dogfall?
我要在一分钟内杀死你
I mean to kill you in one minute, Ned.
或让白加法官吊死你 哪一样?
Or see you hanged at Judge Parker's convenience. Which will it be?
对一个独眼胖汉来说 真是狂言
I call that bold talk for a one- eyed fat man!
看招吧 混蛋
Fill your hand, you son of a bitch!
- 射他们 - 太远 移动得太快
- Shoot them! - Too far, moving too fast.
没胆识? 郭洛达? 不太多
No grit? Rooster Cogburn? Not much!
洛达...
Well, Rooster...
我身中多枪
I'm shot to pieces.
德州人真棒 很厉害的一枪
Hurray for the man from Texas! Some bully shot!
宝 去你的
Damn you, Bo.
你第一次给我骂你的借口
First time you ever give me reason to... cuss you!
救我
Help me!
救我 我在洞里
Help me, I'm in the pit!
这里有一条蛇和一具尸体
There's a snake down here and a skeleton.
不久会有另一具瘦小的
There'll be another one before long. A little spindly one.
你觉得怎样
How do you like it?
救我
Help me. Help me.
求你救我
Please help me!
你是否说你不喜欢?
Are you saying you don't like it?
小妹妹
Baby sister!
- 你在下面吗 - 快点 我很糟
- Are you down there, sis? - Yes, hurry! I'm in a bad way!
好的 支持着
All right, hold on.
我抛条绳给你 把它绑在腋下
I'm gonna pitch you a rope. Slip it under your arms and tie a knot.
不行 我被困住 手也折断了
I can't! I'm caught and my arm is broken.
这里有蛇
There are snakes down here.
它来了
It's in here now!
支持着
Hang on right here.
当你需要一个德州人时他就死了
When you need a damn Texan, he's dead!
我还没有死 支持着
I ain't dead yet, you bushwacker! Hang on!
我要爸爸的枪
I want Papa's gun.
- 我要另外那枚金币 - 不要蛇吗
- I want the other gold piece, too. - You sure you don't want the snake?
- 不要 我要那枚金币 - 算了吧
- No. But I want the gold piece. - Forget it.
但它是我的 我要它
But it's mine and I want it!
那个德州人...救了我两次
That Texican... saved my neck twice.
有一次在他死后
Once after he was dead.
我们要快点治理这个蛇咬伤口
We'll have to do something about this snakebite in a hurry.
小妹妹 举起这只手
Hold this arm up, little sister.
- 我们不能丢下他 - 是我做的
- We can't leave him like this. - I'm the one that's leaving him.
若不找医生 你会和他一样死去
If I don't get you a doctor, you'll be deader than he is.
- 小黑背不到我们 - 我只抓到它
- Little Blackie can't carry us both. - He'll have to. He's all I could catch.
停
Stop it!
我们要停 他快死了
We must stop, he's played out!
停 你在杀死他
Stop it! You're killing him!
别动
Hold it!
把手枪抛入河
Fling them guns into that creek!
我要借用你们的马车
I'm borrowing this wagon off you.
布斯、芬治
Boots! Finch!
布斯
Boots!
你是否郭洛达执法官?
Am I addressing Marshal Reuben J Cogburn?
是 还有陈利和优秀将军
You're addressing him, Chen Lee and General Sterling Price.
我不必问谁是谁了
Well... I'll not ask which is which.
但我会自我介绍
But I'll identify myself.
我是戴格律师
I am lawyer, J Noble Daggett.
- 太惊奇了 - 什么?
- I'll be damned! - What?
你不是...像我们想象的
Well, you're not... exactly what we expected.
你很矮小...你缩水了
You're a little... You're shrunk!
老实告诉你
I'll tell you frankly.
我很想你坐牢 我也做得到
I fully intended to have you jailed, and I'm just the man who could do it.
但美蒂说出事情后我重新考虑
But when Mattie told me the straight of the matter, I had second thoughts.
我仍认为你在这件事上判断错误
I still think you showed poor judgement in this affair,
但你并非我心目中的恶棍
but you're not the scoundrel I took you for.
我向你致谢 和有限的尊敬
You have my thanks and, with certain reservations, my respect.
真好 她怎么样?
How nice! How is sis?
病得很严重
Gravely ill, I'm afraid.
但她仍能处理事务
But still able to direct her affairs.
她吩咐我给你75元的余款
She commissioned me to pay you the balance of the $75 due.
- 她没要求收据吧 - 事实上有的
- She didn't ask for a receipt, did she? - As a matter of fact, she did.
它还包括一笔额外的二百元
You will find that it also covers an additional $200...
报答你救她一命
...for saving her life.
太惊奇了
Well, I will be damned!
她说她回家时要你送她一程
She says that when she goes home, she wants you to take her there.
她不知道自己病得多严重
Poor child does not know how ill she really is.
戴律师 你赌博吗
Lawyer, J Noble Daggett, are you a betting man?
偶尔吧
On occasion.
赌全数和优秀将军 她回到家乡
All of this and General Price, that she makes it back to Yell County.
不要
Oh, no!
先生 不要
No, sir, no, sir!
你为何不去找赖比在韦科的女友
Why didn't you look up La Beef's girl in Waco?
我已经尽了力
I did the best I could.
我把他送回家乡 穿上军服安葬
I took the boy home to be buried in his ranger's suit.
没有女友出现 我相信并无此人
No girl showed up. I don't believe there was one.
你忙于领取赏金
You were too busy collecting the reward.
我只是稍忙 他们忘了赏金数目
I was just a little busy. They forgot how much the reward was.
- 我要帮他们记忆 - 我可想象到
- I had to help them remember. - I can imagine how you did that!
我想你看看这个
This is what I wanted you to see.
爸爸的墓碑跟订造的有分别
Papa's marker was not what was ordered.
我要叫那个笨石匠更换它
I had to make that fool of a stoneman change it.
(罗法伦)
终有一天 妈会在这里
Some day, Mama will be here.
我弟弟和他的家人在那边
And my brother and his family over there.
那边给我的妹妹和她的家人
And that is for my sister and her family.
我会在这里 在爸爸的另一边
And I will be here, on the other side of Papa.
知道我们会在哪里永远相聚很好
It's comforting to know where we'll meet eternity.
洛达 我想你在我身旁安息
I would like you to rest beside me, Rooster.
妹妹 那地方该是给你家人...
Now, sis, that place should be for your family,
你的丈夫、孩子们...
your husband, kids...
你没有亲人 陈利和那只猫不算
You have no kin. I don't count Chen Lee and the cat.
你最终会在哪里? 一片荒野地?
Where would you end up? A neglected patch of weeds?
妹妹 我接受你的建议吧
I might just take you up on that offer, sis.
原谅我不尝试太早搬进来
Excuse me if I don't try to move in too soon.
由你保存爸爸的枪绝对是对的
I think it's only right that you have Papa's gun.
- 它会保住你的性命 - 我不肯定
- It might keep you alive. - I'm not so sure about that.
它走火那次几乎令你丧命
Almost got you killed when it misfired once!
因你在喝醉时上错子弹
Because you loaded it wrong in a state of drunkenness.
- 我要你教我怎么做 - 我会的
- I ought to get you to show me how. - I will.
- 你要买过一匹高马了 - 是的
- Trust you to buy another tall horse. - Yeah...
它不及宝 但史说他能跳四栏杆
He's not as game as Bo, but Stonehill says he can jump a four- rail fence!
你骑马跨栏是有点老和胖了
You're too old and too fat to be jumping horses!
有时间来探望一个胖老人吧
Well, come to see a fat old man some time.